how
specifically things like creatine
actually enhance brain function we you
can take this actually from both ankles
this is like actual cognitive function
first of all does it like if I take
creatine right now am I G to have a
Improvement in cognitive function and
then what about long-term brain as well
so kind of two-part question there about
creatin specific I guess we'll just
start there yeah and then how actually
it's it's doing those if it is at all so
whether you would see a significant
benefit from creatine right now probably
depends a little
you take your dose of 10 grams and like
what are you going to see uh it probably
depends a little bit on your context
but you you probably saw the recent
paper that showed that after one night
of sleep deprivation you know creatine
can overcome some of those deficits
ctively cognitively yeah and that's that
was actually shown um a few years ago uh
with skill rugby skills in rugby players
you may have seen that paper as well
where they had players after a period of
sleep deprivation they gave them either
creative or caffeine and saw similar
improvements in uh like rugby specific
skills compared to a placebo yeah with a
very different mechanism here right
you're talking about a stimulant and
versus a fuel right totally opposite
yeah so uh however you could probably
relate both of those to energetics in
some way because caffeine is overcoming
or it's inhibiting the metabolic
downregulation caused by adenosine um
which is part of what drives you know
sleep pressure in the need for sleep as
you accumulate
metabolites like adenosine they then um
sort of suppress metabolic activity in
the brain um which then is associated
with reduced function and something like
caffeine overcomes that whereas creatine
can acutely uh provide a buffer uh
energetic buffer that allows you to
maintain function in the face of um sort
of increasing metabolic pressure to to
sleep so even though different
mechanisms they kind of maybe converge
on on something similar
I know a lot of people who you know
every time they take Crea in they notice
like an immediate sort of boost of some
kind cognitive function yeah um and
there's there's been a lot of discussion
over the years about whether creatine
negatively impact sleep um for that
reason it's sort of it's slightly
stimulating for some people um I've
certainly found that in myself like if I
take cre I I work out in the afternoon
if I take creatine after my workouts I
don't sleep as well but if I take it
first thing in the morning it's fine
because I've kind of separated it away
and not everybody's like that and
certainly we know that uh responses to
creatine are very heterogeneous right
some people see totally big uh big
responses some people see see smaller
responses and some of it's may be
related to methylation status because
creatine uh when we make our own which
we make a lot of is the most methylation
intensive process in the body you spend
Mo like more of your methal groups
producing creatine than anything else um
and so it could be related to that as
well as you know a whole host of you
know how much creatine do you normally
have in your diet and and things like
that how is creatin actually providing
fuel for your brain um and then on the
second part of that is what's the normal
fuel yeah for our brain when you think
about uh different Energy Systems and I
think people could uh watch endless
lectures from you talking about
different Energy Systems in in uh in
exercise and those principles in some
ways are very similar um in the brain
although the majority of cells in the
brain you know like like we said earlier
derived uh derive energy from glucose
goes through glycolysis then enters the
electron you know the pate and or laxas
pyate goes into the electron transport
chain in the
mitochondria but there's all of that is
done to generate high energy phosphates
fire usually or mainly ATP right so ATP
is your energy current
sort of a much shorter term um energy
currency or that allows you to recycle
ATP when you've used it up is the
phosphocreatine system so um your
creatine is phosphorated with a high
energy phosphate and you use that to
regenerate ATP so for very energetically
expensive uh processes where you can't
get enough energy through that longer
process glycolysis and aerobic
metabolism then the buffer comes from
the fos creatine system and it seems
that even for normal cognitive function
um there is some benefit from having
more of that buffer on board um uh both
acutely and and chronically so just like
your muscles yeah or any other part of
your system they have to rely on energy
the nerves need energy to conduct right
and so people I guess sometimes don't
always grasp the fact that your brain
when we say it's energetically demanding
it's because it's going through a ton of
metabolism we have this connotation that
muscle and Metabolism yeah kind of the
thing but the brain is metabolism yeah
as well your basil metabolic rate the
amount of energy you burn throughout the
day you're fast or slow metabolism all
these things are it's in your brain yeah
as well and so it produces energy much
like anything else it can use fat as a
fuel source theoretically it can use
carbohydrates it could use ketones or
anything else and then creatine just
like it is in your muscle provides that
stochiometry of of one to one right so
not a lot of energy per molecule
creatine so it gets used up and turned
and burned quickly but the upside is it
gives you that energy really fast and so
while you're maybe slow to metabolize
and you mentioned this so we'll bring it
up your brain will actually then
generate lactate yeah so if you're
thinking really hard and thinking a long
time are you like feeling the burn in
your brain is that lactate building up
is that what's happening I don't think
uh lactate doesn't accumulate it just
gets generated and and used you probably
couldn't uh you you could you could
probably measure um so so this is where
I think creating becomes important and
and you potentially if if I put micro
dialysis needles really you know
accurately in certain parts of the brain
and then you you start to upregulate the
use of that Network for a specific
function because there's going to be a
slight delay
between increased ATP production um and
the requirement right you need you you
actually need that energy before you
realize you need it right everything
that we see and do has essentially
already happened because of the time lag
that it takes for us to actually
interpret the those actions so that
energy is needed immediately and it
could be that because of the lag in the
system you know upregulating uh energy
production that's where creating becomes
important in in in a network as you
activate it then you would probably
start to see uh locally if you could
meas you know measure it with uh say
carbon dir metabolism or something you
could have a radio tracer on your on
your lactate and you could see that your
asites which make your lactate for your
neurons um will probably increase
production because your neurons are more
active in that area they're going to
require more energy they've used up
their phosphocreatine system and then
the asites locally going to produce more
lactate none of it's going to accumulate
because it's getting used but flux
through the system is probably
increasing if you enjoyed this clip you
can watch the full episode by clicking
here